A Finding Aid to the Jason Seley Papers, 1928-2003, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jason Seley papers
1928-2003
bulk 1928-1983
Archives of American Art
Seley, Jason, 1919-1983
AAA.selejaso
Archival Resource Key
3 Linear feet
The Jason Seley papers measure 3.0 linear feet and date from 1928 to 2003. The collection documents Seley's career as a sculptor through correspondence with family, colleagues, and art institutions; autobiographical notes, speeches, and other writings; records of an art residency program in Berlin and other professional activity files including sound recordings and a transcript of an interview; personal business records such as ledger books and estate papers; clippings, exhibition catalogs and other printed material; sketches; and photographs and slides of Seley and his sculptures.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The Jason Seley papers measure 3.0 linear feet and date from 1928 to 2003. The collection documents Seley's career as a sculptor through correspondence with family, colleagues, and art institutions; autobiographical notes, speeches, and other writings; records of an art residency program in Berlin and other professional activity files including sound recordings and a transcript of an interview; personal business records such as ledger books and estate papers; clippings, exhibition catalogs and other printed material; sketches; and photographs and slides of Seley and his sculptures.
Biographical / Historical
Jason Seley (1919-1983) was a sculptor and educator in New York, New York, known for creating sculptures out of chrome automobile bumpers.
From 1943-1945 Seley studied with Ossip Zadkine at the Art Students League in New York, and from 1947-1949 he pursued sculpture and taught in Haiti at Le Centre d'Art. In 1950, he received a Fulbright Scholarship to France. While abroad, he traveled and saw the famous Andrea del Verrocchio statue, "Colleoni," and from 1969-1971 he constructed a replica of the statue made from automobile bumpers.
Seley taught at Hofstra, New York University, and was the dean of the art school at Cornell until his death in 1983.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jason Seley papers were donated in two installments, in 1984-1985 by Clara K. Seley, Seley's widow and in 2013 by Richard Heinrich, Seley's former assistant.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1948-1999 (0.7 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1976 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Professional Activity Files, 1949-1983 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1955-1967, 2003 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1948-1984 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1945-1950 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2, OV 5)
Series 7: Photographic Material, 1928-1981 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 2-4, OV 6)
Sound recordings; Interviews; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York
- Correspondence, 1948-1999; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is with Seley's wife Clara, his brother Stephen, his friend Clive Crocker, and various friends, colleagues, and students concerning his family and art-related activities.
  - Clara Seley, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stephen Seley, 1964-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-15)
  - Richard Heinrich, 1970-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clive Crocker, 1974-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Re: Seley Lunch, 1996, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Proposed Seley Exhibition, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Correspondence, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Correspondence, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Correspondence, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34-37)
  - Correspondence, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Correspondence, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Writings, circa 1976; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings consist of miscellaneous notes, autobiographical notes, lecture notes, and speeches.
  - Autobiography Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - The Equestrian Statue: Colleoni II, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Notes for "The Bumper Book", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Speeches, Southeastern College Art Conference, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Professional Activity Files, 1949-1983; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Professional activity files include letters, printed material, and photographs related to Seley's work and projects. Also found are sound recordings which document a lecture Seley gave at Cornell on "Aspects of Modern Sculpture" (1967), a discussion between Seley and Jennings (1967), a tape catalog of the "Sound Show" (1969-1970), and Seley's memorial service in 1983.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Haitan Art, 1949-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Notebook, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56-57)
  - New Sculpture Group, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Transcript of Interview with Jason Seley, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - AINY Seley & Jennings, 1967 March 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Folder 61, Item 1)
  - Aspects of Modern Sculpture, 1967 July 26; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Folder 61, Item 2)
  - Tape Catalog of Sound Show, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Berliner Kunstlerprogram, 1969-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Casper Community College, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mexico, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tennessee Painting & Sculpture Competition, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - United States Information Agency, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spokane Expo, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - New Jersey Cultural Council, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Palm Beach Competition, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sheldon Machlin, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Colleoni II, 1971-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Cornell Then, Sculpture Now, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Allentown, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Farnese, Hercules II, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Memorial Service for Jason Seley, 1983; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Personal Business Records, 1955-1967, 2003; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include five ledgers record expenses (1955-1967) and the estate papers for his Seley's wife, Clara Seley.
  - Ledger Books, 1955-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Estate of Clara Seley, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Also included is a xerox copy of Jason Seley's will.
- Printed Material, 1948-1984; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, obituaries, and a memorial service program documenting Seley's life and career.
  - Clippings, 1949-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1948-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Memorial Service Program and Obituaries, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Artwork, circa 1945-1950; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2, OV 5
  Art works consist of 166 drawings and sketches.
  - Drawings, circa 1945-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29-40)
  - Sketches, circa 1945-1950; Archival Resource Key (Oversize OV 5)
- Photographic Material, 1928-1981; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 2-4, OV 6
  Photographic material, including approximately 1000 slides, shows Seley, his family, assistants working in the studio, and his artworks.
  Photos and slides are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Personal, 1928-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - At Work, 1928-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
  - Works, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Works, 1969-1973; Archival Resource Key (Oversize OV 6)
  - Slides of Gibian Car, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Slides, Cornell University, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Slides, Car at Watkins Glen, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Slides, Colleoni in Newark, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Slides, "Horse and Rider", 1970 June; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Slides, Horse Alone, 1970 June; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Slides, Horse Hightower, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Slides, Details of "Colleoni II", 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Slides, Side Views "Horse and Rider", 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Slides, Partials "Horse and Rider, 1971 July; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Slides, Ric Reverend "Colleoni", 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Slides, Details and Partials of "Colleoni II", 1971 July; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Slides, Charles Uht Originals of Car in Progress, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Slides, Libertone, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Slides, Car, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Slides, Seley and Recent Works, 1976 May; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Slides, Clara Everson, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Slides, Seley at Work, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Slides, For Louis Mezgar, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Slides, Erect Theme Variation I, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Slides, Duplicates, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Slides, Works, 1968-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-9)